<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-10T10:22:15+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alberto Revuelta Arribas</title><subtitle>Software engineer</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Let’s talk contract-based</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/contract-based/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Let’s talk contract-based" /><published>2021-08-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/contract-based</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/contract-based/">&lt;p&gt;But first let’s talk dirty about testing 🐛&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we need them? What are they? Which types are there? Why the !$@* should I write them every time I develop something new?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover why should I take care of the existing ones regarding old code. This last case is the worst one if the logic is hard to understand… 🤦&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to get the grasp about why taking care of existing code and testing is important please read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Clean-Code-Handbook-Software-Craftsmanship/dp/0132350882&quot;&gt;Clean Code: A Handbook of Agile Software Craftsmanship&lt;/a&gt; from Robert C. Martin. Research a bit about the scout rule inside the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover if you feel like you need more knowledge for tackling big legacy code please read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Working-Effectively-Legacy-Michael-Feathers/dp/0131177052&quot;&gt;Working Effectively with Legacy Code&lt;/a&gt; from Michael Feathers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-test-&quot;&gt;What is a test 🤔&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A test is a reusable code from your application which returns the same result over and over again. This means tests are idempotent, it doesn’t matter how many times you run the test suite from your service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result from running your tests the first time and the 147092380th time should be the exact same result ✅. If the test suite fails 🚫 at the 10th run it means you have a 🐛 somewhere. This bug might be related to concurrency, shadowing, etc you name it 🤷&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of programming languages and lots of testing frameworks. Let’s illustrate one simple test making use of one of the best testing frameworks out there from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/&quot;&gt;Ruby programming language&lt;/a&gt;. The framework from this example is &lt;a href=&quot;https://rspec.info/&quot;&gt;Rspec&lt;/a&gt;. The following code should give you a more detailed example 😄:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/rspec.png&quot; alt=&quot;rspec&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-happens-when-there-is-no-testing-&quot;&gt;What happens when there is no testing 👮&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Coverwallet we are big fans of testing, although let’s imagine a different situation where you can end up being. Let’s see how many of you can echo or feel being in this situation 💀&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine entering a new job. All the software tooling you are surrounded with, it’s the one you are familiar with. You have all the technical knowledge required to work with the stack. Although the codebase has around 100.000 lines of code. Moreover, no testing can be found. The documentation you are striving for is shinning by its absence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you are inside the company you are in charge of the huge codebase they have. They ask you to implement some new business logic into the bright new codebase you have now inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are you going to do now? How will you deliver new business logic? How can you be sure that the new logic is not going to have side effects? Are you confident enough to deliver the required new business logic without testing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your software developer guts already are telling you to start things slow and steady. This means to start writing tests for the side business logic affected by this new requirement. You have the approval from the product to spend some huge extra time doing this task. We will focus on this first test of existing behavior from the existing codebase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a firm determination towards the creation of a healthy codebase. How are we going to do it? 🤷&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all let’s talk a bit on which types of testing we have. Let’s just talk about the mainstream tests used among all developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;which-types-of-testing-there-are-&quot;&gt;Which types of testing there are? 🤔&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three types of testing you can develop taking into account your use case. We will give a brief explanation about all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unit-testing&quot;&gt;Unit testing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of testing focuses on the smallest parts of your codebase. Most commonly the public functions you expose into your public service behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;integration-testing&quot;&gt;Integration testing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The integration testing aims to check for more than one layer of dependency inside your codebase. All external requests into any dependency like another service, or a database. As the dependencies can have latency this kind of testing might run a lot slower compared to unit testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;end-to-end-testing-or-functional&quot;&gt;End to end testing or functional&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last tests can be seen as chained integration testing. The focus of this testing is to check your whole application works as expected. Checking everything you can pull the thread from one end into the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can think of an example of this testing as tests which checks the user interface any user can make use of. The goal of this testing is to actually corroborate that the end user can perform what she wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;testing-practices-available&quot;&gt;Testing practices available&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of testing software approaches. We will talk about the one we are going to use during this post. We will talk about Test Driven Design TDD or Behavior Driven Design BDD. This approaches come from the test-first programming concepts from Extreme Programming EX begun in 1999.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TDD is a development process were the requirements from the new features transform into test cases. Before starting to develop we ensure all the requirements are being exposed to the application as testing suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of information on how TDD or BDD works, although we will highlight the 3 big steps from this development process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;red-step-&quot;&gt;Red step 🔴&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first step we will have to add into our test suite the new failing tests. This means we will define tests with classes, modules, functions, methods and attributes which do not exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After adding this step we will make sure the tests work as we expect by running them. Moreover you can run all of the existing test suite to check all the other tests are green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;green-step-&quot;&gt;Green step 🟢&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is where we will actually develop the logic for the previously defined tests. In this process we will provide the required software to make the tests turn from 🔴 red to 🟢 .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is up to us to decide which solution we want to deliver to fulfill the tests we have written. This step has to be the quickest one. We will have to deliver the first working solution we can think of for validating our existing new test suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;refactor-step-&quot;&gt;Refactor step ⚪&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this third step we will refactor the provided logic. This step is safe as if we made any change which makes our new tests fails. We can always return to our last green commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finishing up with this step we can go back into the red step to add new uncaught tests. Or to the green step if you have delivered more logic than the intended in the refactoring step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tdd-existing-approaches&quot;&gt;TDD existing approaches&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can differentiate two TDD approaches which are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;chicago-or-traditional-tdd&quot;&gt;Chicago or traditional TDD&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This TDD approach proposes a inside out approach. It starts from the domain model objects into the controller/interface layer. This approach is usually associated with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Test-Driven-Development-Kent-Beck/dp/0321146530&quot;&gt;Test Driven Development: By Example&lt;/a&gt; from Kent Beck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;london-tdd&quot;&gt;London TDD&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand this other TDD approach focus on the outside in approach. It focus in the controller/interface layer up until reaching the domain domain objects. This approach is usually associated with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Growing-Object-Oriented-Software-Guided-Signature/dp/0321503627&quot;&gt;Growing Object-Oriented Software, Guided by Tests&lt;/a&gt; from Freeman and Pryce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is up to you how you want to perform your development process. Maybe this process is not right for you. I would give it a try first. There is quite a learning curve, although it will pay off. Moreover the testing you will provide will improve exponentially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the previous shown code in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/&quot;&gt;Ruby the programming language&lt;/a&gt; we can see an example on how to test using &lt;a href=&quot;https://rspec.info/&quot;&gt;Rspec&lt;/a&gt;. Although testing and these testing approaches are not bound into any language nor test framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about TDD approach you can check out this &lt;a href=&quot;https://team-agile.com/2021/02/06/chicago-and-london-style-tdd/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;. Moreover to learn more about TDD you can check the video: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EZ05e7EMOLM&amp;amp;ab_channel=DevTernity&quot;&gt;TDD, Where Did It All Go Wrong&lt;/a&gt; or the books:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Test-Driven-Development-Kent-Beck/dp/0321146530&quot;&gt;Test Driven Development: By Example&lt;/a&gt; from Kent Beck.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.es/Growing-Object-Oriented-Software-Guided-Signature/dp/0321503627&quot;&gt;Growing Object-Oriented Software, Guided by Tests&lt;/a&gt; from Freeman and Pryce.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-am-i-going-to-test-it-&quot;&gt;How am I going to test it? 😓&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it’s time to decide how we want to test the existing huge codebase we have to maintain. Te new business request involves some changes in an existing endpoint from the service. To test this existing code we would follow the London TDD approach. I know we have already the code and how TDD clashes with existing code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To wrap up the important thing we want to highlight from the London TDD approach is to test from the outside in. Test things from the outside of the service towards the business logic into the core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;service-example&quot;&gt;Service example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s give an example on how is the existing service. Although I would just highlight the code we are going to work with. This will make it somewhat easier as the goal of this post is to learn how to test making use of a type of mocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The service we have inherited is in charge of dealing with the adoption of animals from a local shelter. The service is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://phoenixframework.org/&quot;&gt;Phoenix&lt;/a&gt; application which makes use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://elixir-lang.org/&quot;&gt;Elixir programing language&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first and only part we will start testing is for the adoption of an animal from the foster local shelter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;elixir-coding-example&quot;&gt;Elixir coding example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the sample code from the controller file: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lib/foster_shelter_bigotitos_web/controllers/animal_controller.ex&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/controller_generator.png&quot; alt=&quot;controller_generator&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This code is a piece of smelly cheese as you all can see. All the logic is inside the controller from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://phoenixframework.org/&quot;&gt;Phoenix&lt;/a&gt; application. Although we will try to test the existing code making a segregation from the different layers we have in the shown example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-start-testing-&quot;&gt;Let’s start testing! 🚀&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code we want to test is a request into our server. Lets see from the available routes which is the path for the request:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/phx_routes.png&quot; alt=&quot;controller_generator&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see &lt;a href=&quot;https://phoenixframework.org/&quot;&gt;Phoenix&lt;/a&gt; works with paths: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;animal_path&lt;/code&gt; is the only path we will be interested in. Both PATCH and PUT HTTP requests go through the same controller update/2 method. Now that we know how the users enter our service lets test the controller from the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;testing-errors-from-controller---green&quot;&gt;Testing errors from controller - Green&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this first approach we will test the existing behavior from the controller. It doesn’t matter the parameters from the shelter animal from the adoption request. The only important thing from the actual adoption request is the customer email. This information will allow us to retrieve all the customer information from the service. If we can’t make this relationship the adoption request will fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have put as an example below a possible testing suite which more less fits the actual behavior from the legacy codebase we have inherited. The code needed for this test suite is massive. Moreover we need to actually create the database items for the controller testing. This means we have database dependency inside our testing suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of code from the actual test suite which is screaming to be moved out of this context. The way a test needs to be structured, all the dependencies it requires it will also tell you where it really needs to be. Without further ado check in the example below a simple testing for this legacy codebase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/test_controller_generators.png&quot; alt=&quot;test_controller_generator&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;refactor&quot;&gt;Refactor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were following TDD now would be a good time to apply the refactor step. In a proper TDD flow we would have done this test first (red step). Afterwards we would have done the implementation for the behavior (green step). Finally we would follow the last refactor step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have the confidence from the fresh new tests to back our refactor approaches. We have now captured all the tests from the controller from the service. Now would be a good opportunity to move all that fat logic away from the controller and put it somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This step will involve the creation of a new test suite regarding the required business logic which is actually not fully being tested right now. If we see the logic from the controller the only thing being displayed is the animal being adopted. On the other hand if we do not find the user we retrieve a nil which the controller then parses into an error tuple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;special-refactor-step&quot;&gt;Special refactor step&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this special case we already have the logic we need to move from the controller into a new module. On one hand we could move the logic from the controller into a new module and check if controller tests had been broken. On the other hand we can define the test suite covering the new module containing all the moved logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prefer to do the latter option so let’s define the test suite. This suite is going to cover the logic from the adoption request from our foster shelter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/action_logic_test.png&quot; alt=&quot;action_logic_test&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;real-refactor-step&quot;&gt;Real refactor step&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s move all the logic from the controller into another module keeping all the behavior as expected already being tested in the previous test suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/action_logic.png&quot; alt=&quot;action_logic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After running the previously created for the new module we can see the behavior has been captured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/check_testing_action.png&quot; alt=&quot;check_testing_action&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have defined the logic inside another module lets call from the controller the new module with the existing logic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/clean_controller.png&quot; alt=&quot;clean_controller&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now how can we be sure we have the expected behavior from our service? Let’s make a quick call for the controller tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/check_controller_test.png&quot; alt=&quot;check_controller_test&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens if my controller tests fail in this last step? This means you did more than just refactor in this step. Also could be you missed some behavior from the logic from the adoption request from the users of the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;contract-based-testing-&quot;&gt;Contract based testing 📑&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as we have got right now we didn’t change the logic itself. Just rearrange the parameters from one place into another. Lets move a bit the dependency modules we have right now. We can spot we are making use of the database calls from the next modules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/database_modules.png&quot; alt=&quot;database_modules&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we check the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Animals&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Customers&lt;/code&gt; modules we can see the modules are also making calls into the Repo module. I will not dive into what exactly it is. The important thing here is that the Repo module makes calls into the database. In our testing environment the Repo module will make calls into the testing database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the next steps we will move the database dependencies into the function parameters itself. We can see the adoption business action logic being applied to contracts inside the own business action module. The following code would represent the abstraction from the database modules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/action_contract_logic.png&quot; alt=&quot;action_contract_logic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we run the tests again from before we can still see that the tests are still running. We didn’t change anything yet 🤓&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;test-dependencies&quot;&gt;Test dependencies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have spotted previously we have some database dependency for the testing. Right now our &lt;a href=&quot;https://phoenixframework.org/&quot;&gt;Phoenix&lt;/a&gt; service is quite smart. In the tasks our service performs we can see the following ones:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/mix_exs.png&quot; alt=&quot;mix_exs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can spot where the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mix test&lt;/code&gt; task does not only perform the test task. It also performs the creation for the test database. Moreover the migrations for the test database. This means before running the tests the application sets up the test database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what happens if we make the &lt;a href=&quot;https://phoenixframework.org/&quot;&gt;Phoenix&lt;/a&gt; application dumb. Let’s make the testing dependency raise issues. For this purpose we have to delete the test alias and make it only perform the tests. We have to change the test mix alias:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;test: [&quot;test&quot;]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s now perform a test correlated mix task. Right afterwards lets perform again: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mix test&lt;/code&gt; again and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/db_not_working.png&quot; alt=&quot;db_not_working&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see we didn’t change anything from the test files themselves. We just deleted the database related to the testing. This would relate as if we had a request into another service and the other service was down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t change the tests from our service by any means. Although we changed the configuration required for the tests. Now we have to question ourselves if the testing we have right now is the testing we want to perform for our service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mocking-time-&quot;&gt;Mocking time! 🚀&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it’s time to give a reshape for our testing suite. We will not change the test implementation itself. Although we will mock the database dependency. This will mean we have to create the module mocks for this purpose. The following modules have to be defined in a place where elixir compiles, as we need them available for the tests. We can put these modules inside: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;test/support&lt;/code&gt; for example. The module mocks would look something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/mocks.png&quot; alt=&quot;mocks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please bear in mind that you can check with the database dependency how the output for the required methods is required. Like any other testing dependency you have to double check the contract you will be mocking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we can change the testing suite and make it use our own mocks. This will mean we don’t need the database connection for passing our tests. The code changed for this will be the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/contract-based/action_contract_test.png&quot; alt=&quot;action_contract_test&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been quite a journey for decoupling the database dependency out from the test suite. If you run the tests again you can see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://phoenixframework.org/&quot;&gt;Phoenix&lt;/a&gt; application still tries to check the database connection. Although afterwards the tests end up all green to our liking.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="software" /><category term="development" /><category term="contract" /><category term="based" /><category term="end" /><category term="to" /><category term="testing" /><category term="elixir" /><category term="ruby" /><summary type="html">But first let’s talk dirty about testing 🐛</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First job/internship</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/first-job/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First job/internship" /><published>2020-11-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/first-job</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/first-job/">&lt;p&gt;We all have been there, we all have been through it, and you will too 💪. We all, as humans beings, need to conquer the very first job/internship from our lives. We might have different personal motives to accomplish this personal milestone. Moreover the end of this goal may shift from one another. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You might need this job to validate yourself to someone. That someone could be your parent, someone you love or yourself 💕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You could be in need for a job for your own survival.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You may have the passion for doing that job.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You may want to help others by doing so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arming-up-for-the-battle-&quot;&gt;Arming up for the battle 🛠&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having stated some examples of job motivation, now you need to root for it. You have to apply for that job and present yourself. You will have to define yourself and state your strengths. Trust me we all have them. If you don’t see them yourself ask anyone in your social circle 😀&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to prepare yourself for this moment is to be able to answer the following question: Why? Why do you want or need to have that job. Is it because the job aligns with who you are? Is it because you want to learn how to do that job?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could also be the rewards from the job which are appealing to you. The rewards can be economic 💰, moral, new experiences and a whole lot of other reasons. The main point here is that you have to stand your ground if someone ask you why you are working there. You have to be contented and thrilled if someone asks you about what you do for a living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the reason is crystal clear, you will need to study which projects or tasks does that job implies. Research 📚 how is the recent history of that specific job and who you will be working with. Its better if you have an idea what kind of tasks you will be in charge of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will face tough questions and mostly blunt assumptions about yourself. The best way to surpass this might be to expose your vulnerabilities 🎯. We trust people who fail, who seems approachable, who isn’t afraid to show themselves as how they truly are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All humans make mistakes. If they expect a perfect employee wish them luck hiring a robot 🤖. We as humans do not trust people who seem flawless, we don’t empathize with people who are idealized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will succeed on your first try for that job application 🙌 or you will learn a valuable experience 😎. Bear in mind you have to enjoy your journey, there will be ups and there will be downs. Although we have to always learn from our experiences 🙂&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;now-what-&quot;&gt;Now what? 😅&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations! 🎉 You made it 🏁&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait… Now you will have even more questions than before 😅&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After being relieved from the main question you had before: will they choose me? now you will face now lots of questions❓ about your new journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can imagine the most important one: will I be able to do it? will I be able to keep up the expectations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous section I wrote about vulnerability and failure so lets dive more into this. Lets talk about some feeling you might have as you do that job. We will get to know a syndrome which you might have felt previously. Because you are not the only one, and furthermore you will not be the last one by far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impostor-syndrome&quot;&gt;Impostor syndrome&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of resources regarding this topic. I will leave some of them at the bottom of this post. The first time this syndrome was studied was in a group of female college students by Pauline Rose Clance and Suzanne Imes (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paulineroseclance.com/pdf/ip_high_achieving_women.pdf&quot;&gt;research paper&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets define the impostor syndrome as an individual feeling. This feeling can unravel other kind of deep feelings but that might be a good idea to tackle them with some help from 👨‍⚕️👩‍⚕️🏥&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impostor syndrome is a individual feeling, but at the same time, it impacts the whole world society. We all have felt it someway at any time span throughout our lives. Its a feeling you suffer when you expect some outside input from something you provide. What you expose could be anything, from some document your superior asked you to your mom asking you to take care of some household errands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feeling is living from time to time inside of us and will show in different shapes. A good way to tackle this feeling is listening to other peoples experiences. Being able to empathize with others and get to know their vulnerabilities will help our own impostor syndrome. Its hard to think the cure for the impostor syndrome is to talk about it among your environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope you can find the courage to speak about with your social environment 💪&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you scored that first job speak about it. If you didn’t get it, moreover, speak about it.
Make visible the struggles 🤕 from your experiences, break the chain ⛓ of flawless people. Who by the way… don’t exist 🤣&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance I failed A LOT until I found something I really enjoyed 😅&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@rajeefmk/why-does-software-developers-suffer-from-imposter-syndrome-ccf961d0c29a&quot;&gt;Medium blog post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZQUxL4Jm1Lo&amp;amp;ab_channel=TED-Ed&quot;&gt;TED-ed video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paulineroseclance.com/pdf/ip_high_achieving_women.pdf&quot;&gt;First research paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="software" /><category term="developer" /><category term="first" /><category term="job" /><category term="internship" /><summary type="html">We all have been there, we all have been through it, and you will too 💪. We all, as humans beings, need to conquer the very first job/internship from our lives. We might have different personal motives to accomplish this personal milestone. Moreover the end of this goal may shift from one another. For example:</summary></entry></feed>